Guide to the Student Health Services Records 1929-2015
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Student Health Services Records
1929-2015
1986-2010
Oregon State University. Student Health Services.
RG 023
4.00 cubic feet 4 boxes
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Student Health Services Records document the administration and provision of health services to Oregon State University students. The records address a variety of health and medical topics such as communicable diseases, vaccinations, patient privacy, and medical records. Student Health Services was established at Oregon Agricultural College in 1916.
Historical Note:
Student Health Services was established at Oregon Agricultural College in 1916 in a single room within the Men’s Gymnasium. The following year Student Health moved into the frame building now known as the Hattie Redmond Women and Gender Center (formerly Benton Annex) and stayed in that location until the Student Health Service Building was constructed in 1936 with federal funds provided by the Works Progress Administration (WPA). The Student Health Service Building is now known as Plageman Hall, in honor of Erna Plageman, a long-time student health administrator at Oregon State.
When it was established, Student Health was under the purview of Clair V. Langton, Dean of Health and Physical Education. In the early 1930s, Student Health was placed under the supervision of the Dean of the University of Oregon Medical School in Portland. By the early 1960s, responsibility for oversight for Student Health had moved to the Dean of Students at Oregon State University.
Student Health Services is funded by student fees and provides a full range of health services -- clinical services; prevention and wellness programs including vaccinations, alcohol and drug abuse prevention education; and sexual assault care and advocacy.
Oregon State College. Student Health Services.; Oregon State College--Students.; Oregon State College. Student Health Services; Oregon State University--Students.; Oregon State University. Student Health Services
College students--Health and hygiene; College students--Medical care--Oregon--Corvallis.
Colleges and Universities; Medicine and Health; Oregon; Corvallis
These materials were received by the former University Archives and the Special Collections and Archives Research Center in multiple transfers from 2000 thru 2018. The early Student Health Service records were transferred prior to 1981, probably in the 1970s.
Collection is open for research.
Additional materials documenting Student Health Services at Oregon State are available in the Student Affairs Records (RG 102) and the Student Incidental Fees Committee Records (RG 258). An extensive history of student health at Oregon State (through 1969) is available in the Memorabilia Collection. Photographs of early student health service facilities and staff are part of the Amy Cyrus Sewing Book and Photographs (MSS Cyrus).
The Student Health Services Records are arranged in 5 series: 1. Policies and Procedures, 1929-2015; 2. Meeting Minutes, 1986-2010; 3. Financial Records, 1937-1992; 4. Publications 1991-1998; and 5. Subject Files, 1929-2014.
The Student Health Services Records document the administration and provision of health and medical services to Oregon State University students. The bulk of the collection consists of policies and procedures (Series 1) and the meeting records of the Leadership and Management Teams and the nursing staff (Series 2). These series document the establishment and implementation of protocols for the application of medical treatment; screening of students for communicable diseases; vaccination requirements; safety and emergencies; and medical records and patient privacy.
A small quantity of financial records provide information about the costs incurred to provide medical care to Army students on campus during World War II.
The subject files document programs and activities as well as health and medical topics. Of note are materials documenting health services provided to youth participating in 4-H summer programs on campus during the 1930-1950s; interactions with the Oregon State Board of Health and the central administration of Oregon State College; biographical information about Student Health professional staff in the 1930s-1940s; the medical excuses policy for student absences; and the Student Health response to the SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome) outbreak. Annual reports, statistical summaries, and staff newsletters round out the collection.
- Policies and Procedures, 1929-2015; Series 1
  Series 1 consists of Student Health policies and procedures that guide staff in the application of medical treatment; screening of students for communicable diseases, such as tuberculosis; equipment handling; and the management of patient information and medical records. Procedures pertaining to safety and emergencies; the Hepatits B virus, HIV (or AIDS), and reportable diseases; student workers, waste disposal; immunizations; and quarantines are outlined in these materials. Many of the policy statements have handwritten annotations of revisions and updates. Most folders have an index listing the policies and procedures that are included. These materials cover the late 1920s thru mid-1950s and the mid-1980s through 2015.
  - Policies and Procedures Health Services, 1929-1947 (Box-folder 1.01)
  - Routine Procedure, 1938-1954 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - Standard Procedures, 1941-1952 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1986-1994 (Box-folder 1.04)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1986-2006 (Box-folder 1.05)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 1.06)
  - Master Policy Procedure Manual, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 1.07-1.09)
    3 folders
  - Policies Procedures, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Policies Procedures, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Policies Procedures, 1993-2003 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Policy and Procedures, 1996-2006 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1997-2004 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Policies Procedures, 2004-2007 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Policies and Procedures, 2007-2010 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Policies and Procedures, 2008-2015 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Policy and Procedure Statements, 2000-2013 (Box-folder 1.18-1.20)
- Meeting Minutes, 1986-2010; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of agendas, minutes, and related documentation for meetings of the leadership and nursing staff of Student Health Services as well as other shorter-term Student Health Committees. The Leadership and Management Team meetings primarily address administration and management of Student Health; the nursing staff meetings includes updates as well as discussions of protocols and procedures.
  - Ancillary Services Department Meeting, 1995 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Building Enhancement Committee, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Lab and X-ray Committee, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Leadership Team, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 2.01)
  - Leadership Team, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 2.02)
  - Leadership Team, 1999-2006 (Box-folder 2.03)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2.04)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 2.05)
  - Leadership Team Meeting Minutes, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 2.06)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 2.07)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 2.08)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 2.09)
  - Leadership Team Minutes, 2009-2010 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Managment Team Meeting Minutes, 1995 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Management Team Meeting Minutes, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 2.12-2.13)
    2 folders
  - Nursing Staff Meetings, 1986-1994 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Nursing Staff Meetings, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - Nursing Staff Meetings, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - Nursing Staff Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 3.01)
  - Nursing Staff Meetings, 1999-2002 (Box-folder 3.02)
  - Nursing Meeting Minutes, 2002-2007 (Box-folder 3.03)
  - Occupational Health Planning Committee, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 3.04)
  - Quality Improvement Assurance Committee, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 3.05)
  - Reach Out Promotion Committee, 1995-2001 (Box-folder 3.06)
  - Service Heads Meetings, 1992 (Box-folder 3.07)
- Financial Records, 1937-1992; Series 3
  Series 3 provides limited information about the income and expenses of Student Health, primarily during the 1930s-1950s. Budget information for the late 1980s-early 1990s is also included. Of special note is information about the costs incurred to provide healthcare to Army students on campus during World War II.
  - Army Financial Reports by Mr. Burrell, 1944 (Box-folder 3.08)
  - Inventory Equipment, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 3.09)
  - Food Costs, 1937-1947 (Box-folder 3.10)
  - Health Services Charges, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 3.11-3.12)
  - Budgetary Information Income Summary and Reports, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 3.13)
- Publications, 1991-1998; Series 4
  Series 4 consists of newsletters published during the 1990s that are primarily intended for Student Health Services employees.
  - Student Health Center Newsletter, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3.14)
    Staff newsletter for Student Health Services employees.
  - Vital Signs, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 3.15)
    This newsletter was initially focussed on staff and provided updates, kudos, and announcements of interest and use to Student Health Services employees. The newsletter transitioned into a publication for the whole campus in the later issues and included more information about health promotion and wellness programs and activities.
- Subject Files, 1929-2014; Series 5
  Series 5 consists of materials on a variety of subjects that address the administration of Student Health Services; interactions between Student Health and other units at Oregon State and state agencies, such as the Oregon State Board of Health; the medical excuses policy for student absences developed in 1998; the Student Health response to the SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome) outbreak; and student satisfaction with Student Health programs and services. This series includes three annotated telephone guides used by Student Health nurses to address questions received by telephone on general medical and health matters, pediatrics, and obstetrics and gynecology. This series includes statististics and annual reports summarizing clients served, programs, activities.
  Other materials of note include records documenting health services provided to youth participants in 4-H summer programs on the Oregon State campus from the 1930s through mid-1950s and biographical information about health services professional staff in the 1930s-1940s. The Executive Offices correspondence documents interactions between the Student Health Service Director and senior administrators, including the College President, regarding budgets, facilities, and staffing. Memoranda to all deans and department heads are also included with this correspondence.
  - 4-H Club, 1930-1948 (Box-folder 3.16)
  - 4-H Club Records, 1948-1955 (Box-folder 3.17)
  - Announcements, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 3.18)
    Announcements to all Oregon State University faculty and staff regarding the flu vaccine shortage.
  - Announcements, 2014 (Box-folder 3.19)
    Announcements of new programs sponsored by Student Health.
  - Annual Reports, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 3.20)
  - Army, 1943 (Box-folder 3.21)
    October 1943.
  - Correspondence - Associate Director (Susan Longerbeam), 1993 (Box-folder 3.22)
  - Correspondence General, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 3.23)
  - Executive Offices Correspondence, 1929-1934 (Box-folder 3.24)
  - Executive Offices Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 3.25)
  - Executive Offices, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 3.26)
  - Executive Offices, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 3.27)
  - Executive Offices, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 3.28)
  - Executive Offices, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3.29)
  - Executive Offices, 1942-1952 (Box-folder 3.30)
  - Executive Offices, 1952-1961 (Box-folder 4.01)
  - Food Services, 1940-1960 (Box-folder 4.02)
  - Former Health Services Professional Staff, 1930-1945 (Box-folder 4.03-4.04)
  - Infirmary Patient Record Statistics, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4.05)
  - Medical Excuses Policy, 1998 (Box-folder 4.06)
  - Oregon State Board of Health, 1930-1957 (Box-folder 4.07)
  - Oregon State Board of Health Bulletin, 1936-1948 (Box-folder 4.08)
  - Physical Plant Department OSC, 1931-1961 (Box-folder 4.09)
  - Product List for Equipment Ordering, 1996 (Box-folder 4.10)
  - Radiation Safety Information, 1986-2001 (Box-folder 4.11)
  - Student Volunteer Internship Opportunities, 2000 (Box-folder 4.12)
  - Shaw Supply Company, 1929-1954 (Box-folder 4.13)
  - SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome) Response Report, 2003 (Box-folder 4.14)
  - State Board of Health Correspondence, 1933-1956 (Box-folder 4.15)
  - Student Satisfaction Survey, 2000 (Box-folder 4.16-4.17)
  - Survey and Construction Reports, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 4.18)
  - Pediatric Telephone Advice, 2002 (Box-folder 4.19)
  - Telephone Triage Obstetrics and Gynecology, 2014 (Box-folder 4.20)
  - Telephone Triage Protocols for Nurses, 2002 (Box-folder 4.21)